Okay.
They come to yoga and then
uh
He's quoting uh Master Shantideva. By
the way,
Egor and Anna, we're still going out to
dinner, okay? And you pay.
But it's just pizza, okay?
Okay. All right. Uh just kidding.
I mean, we are. Okay. Uh
It says here uh Master Shantideva said,
one good thing about suffering, like
when I had my surgery,
uh
your pride breaks.
You know, before the
doctor want to cut you up, you are you
are a little bit gishy Michael.
Then
then they say, "Okay, take off your your
clothes, go in there."
You know, we're going to
what do you call?
Cut the turkey. And
uh
then suddenly you become very gentle.
Okay. It makes people gentle, I think.
Uh
you can be very proud about your
position.
Or you can say, "I'm a big teacher."
or something like that. But if you get
really sick or you have some real
trouble,
then it it helps your attitude.
Uh you don't you're not so proud, okay?
After that, it helps you become a better
person, I think so.
So I wanted to offer an
operation to everybody.
No, I'm just kidding. Okay. Carla and
Carla and
also when you have some
medical problem or family problem, then
you
you're more
compassionate towards other people who
have family problem or medical problem.
Also, you start to think, "Why I have
this problem?
Why I got this sickness?" And then you
start to
keep your morality a little bit better.
Not much.
A little bit better, okay? All right.
Uh Dharma Sela Tichila Nini Neko Sego
[__] really
uh member really Machung Yang Chugda
Sunyong the name is Sunyong Sunki. Say
Ningo.
Uh
Ningo means uh
lousy, okay? Lousy. Not so good.
Okay. Ningo means uh lousy. And uh if
you're Dharma person,
especially if you're a monk or nun, then
uh should be
satisfied.
Uh you get some lousy clothes
or you get so I would I usually wear the
same clothes for 1 year without washing.
And
just kidding.
Uh
maybe 2 weeks. Um
then uh
but uh the nice thing about become a
monk or nun is that you don't you don't
have to worry about checking all the
shops in Kyoto. I want to buy a better
suit or I want some better shoes or
something like that, okay? You just get
used to
uh whatever you can whatever you have if
you are happy.
Okay. Say Duchung.
Chokshe.
Duchung.
Three people answered. You ready?
Everybody, Duchung.
That's better. Chokshe.
Yeah, Duchung means
uh I don't need much.
And Chokshe means I like the stuff I
already have. We are all friends. My old
shoes, my old pants.
Uh
we are all friends, okay? So Duchung
means
and I I don't feel like I need to go buy
new things. The old ones are still okay.
And
uh Chokshe means uh
I'm happy to be with my old shoes and my
old pants and
you know, my wife is not happy, but I'm
happy. Okay. Uh Dharma Sela Tichung
Neke. So that's applies to your clothes
and your
house where you stay.
So I'm proud to say I have the smallest
legal house in my town.
Okay? And
800 square feet, so very small.
And and I'm happy. I even cannot clean
more than half of it. I cannot clean.
Cuz I'm too busy, you know? So I I don't
want some big place and
people We went to San Diego. People say,
"Let's buy this
$25 million house." And I'm like,
first of all, I cannot even afford the
mailbox.
And secondly,
uh I don't want to spend all my time
paying those mortgage and
and and cleaning this place and fixing
all the broken things. I think rich
people spend all their time fixing
broken things.
I'm not interested. I don't want to be a
slave to a house.
I don't want to be a slave to some
expensive clothes and then I have to
take them to the dry cleaner.
Then I have to go make prostration to
the dry cleaner. I don't dry cleaner
became my stupa.
Yeah.
I don't have time, okay? I just don't
have time.
So Sunyong the name of song. When you
have uh
here it says
Pakpe Rigshi. Say Pakpe.
Rig.
Shi.
These are four things which Aryas
supposed to like. Okay? And by the way,
in this book,
they don't tell you what is the fourth.
So grandpa always go and get the fourth
for you, okay? Because I have John
Brady's database.
Okay.
Uh
Number one, Chug Ningo Sunki Chokshe Pa
means
uh
you know, if I have some old jeans and I
have old shirt old shirt is more
comfortable, right? Old shoes.
These are the new shoes. I wear them
just for you, okay?
When I leave, I immediately take them
off.
Uh
so anyway, just anything is okay. My
clothing is okay. Number one. How many?
Uh
four. Okay. Number two.
Uh Neme Ningo Sunki Chokshe Pa.
Uh
You don't need a big fancy bed, okay?
They
When I go on these tours,
they get me a big room, they get me a
big fancy bed.
And I sleep in one little corner of the
bed.
Then I have to make the whole stupid
bed, you know? It's too big, you know?
And
I get lost. I don't know where I am.
So
usually I just sleep in
in one piece of the bed.
That's my territory. My wife has her
territory.
You know, I'm used to I can't even roll
over cuz I will go to the other person's
territory.
So I'm used to simple simple bed, okay?
I like the bed here in Japan. It's uh
simple. Many are simple, low,
not too high. It feels more comfortable.
Okay, number three.
Sunyong Ningo Sunki Chokshe Pa.
Uh your food, okay? Nothing fancy. And
uh
When I travel,
uh people always want to make my food,
you know? And they come to me on the
first day, "What would you like to eat
for
lunch?" And I say cuz I don't eat in the
morning.
Then I say, "I'll take granola." You
know? And then the next day they come
and
"What would you like to eat for lunch?"
I say, "Granola."
Third day, granola. Fourth day, granola.
Then they stop asking.
It's the same thing every day. I don't
care.
You know, I really don't care. And so
just
you can waste a lot of time cooking
fancy things and
even to go to a nice restaurant. We went
last night to a nice restaurant. It took
4 5 6 hours.
Uh
but we had a good meeting
with
Jamie and Bo. Where are you?
Can you stand up? Don't be shy. Jamie
and Bo.
Yeah.
And your assistant your assistant.
Uh
So they have a special website called
the knowledge base.
They put 5,000 videos on there.
And they have 5,000 more they are fixing
now.
So it's 10,000 videos and it's free.
And they worked very hard to make the
descriptions. Both working on the
Lamrim.
She finished, I think, five courses. I'm
not sure. Am I right? Five courses. Six
courses.
And uh she connected to the original
uh language. And you know, she she did
all this work. She and her assistant uh
did all of this work. So the 14 years of
Lamrim,
uh you can you can watch uh 14 years for
free
uh on the knowledge base. Let's give
them another hand.
They always give me the same answer when
I we go out to dinner once a year or
once every 10 years and uh
I say you guys need any money and they
say no.
They're the only people who say no.
And
they say no we we don't need we okay.
And but they do take donation, okay? So
if you watch the
the classes on their site I encourage
you to to give some donation. They
survive from that. They don't ask me for
money. They're the only people who don't
ask me for money.
Seriously. So
so you should help them. I hope.
Okay.
I took them to dinner and they said no.
Uh
Number four, Bol and Gomala Gawa.
Bol and Gomala Gawa means uh
instead of collecting new things and
buying new things and and like that, I
rather spend the time doing my practice
and doing my meditation, okay? Yeah, you
don't have time for both.
Okay, let the 71.9
year old man tell you.
Your life will pass very quickly. You
will be 71.9 or 72.9 or very soon, okay?
It's It's not just me, it's also you,
okay?
And you don't have time to
to go buy the new clothes and and buy
new house and
even you have the money. I have money. I
have enough money. I can buy several
houses.
But I don't have time to to buy them and
I don't have time to take care of them
and I I don't want to.
I don't want to spend my time like that,
you know? So okay.
Uh so Gomala Gawa means uh in this way
you can have enough time
to to do your practice, okay? And and
you can be quiet. You can do your
meditation every day. You can do your
yoga.
You can do your study. You can enjoy.
You can really enjoy your life
if you don't want too many things, okay?
All right.
Next picture.
They have these pictures of you know,
the family finds their beautiful house
and we call the American dream. This is
the American dream, you know?
The happy family which doesn't exist.
And
they find the big beautiful house and
and then after before they find the big
beautiful house
they are not happy. After they find the
big beautiful house, somehow they become
happy.
And then you know, you can waste your
whole time like this, okay? If you
wonder
does anybody find a big beautiful house
and is happy? I didn't find anyone yet.
Maybe maybe there is somebody in Hawaii,
I don't know.
I haven't been there, okay? Lately.
There was in the sutras
a story about a
lumber seller, wood seller.
And
he invited the
the Buddha to his house and there's a
summer wall.
And
outside and then inside his wall outside
there looks like there's a hole.
And uh
he asked the Buddha, what do you think
is in the hole, you know, in in my
backyard?
And Buddha said it's it's very serious
poison. It's a pollution hole.
You shouldn't touch it. You shouldn't
get near to it.
You know, so for many years he didn't
touch it. Then I guess his friend came
over to his house
and he's curious and he dug dug in that
hole
and he found a lot of gold.
And
he went to Buddha. He said, you cheated
me. You you told me there's a poison in
the hole. He said, no, I was correct.
There is poison in the hole, okay? A lot
of money will ruin your life, okay? Too
much Most people
become more unhappy after they get
money, a lot of money, okay?
And they waste their time.
They waste their time, okay?
Yeah, so he got in trouble.
He got in trouble about that.
Uh here's another nice picture that I
enjoy.
Uh
Tsongkhapa, so he's
he's the greatest I've been working on
his book for 12 years. In the morning
every day I get up
6:00 I work on Tsongkhapa. I do my
meditation.
I read some
scripture to help my bad habit.
And then I I translate. So I translate
for five or six hours every morning.
And so I
I I'm last 12 years I'm working on his
book. He he wrote a book about
emptiness. To This morning I reached
1600 pages.
Uh yeah.
I try to give you for Christmas present,
okay? I'm
I have 80 pages left.
Nothing. So I can finish.
Why I say that?
His book is unbelievable, unbelievable.
20% unbelievable and he was very famous.
He had many students.
And he started to collect a lot of
money.
And then he said, okay.
Time to go, you know?
And they said, what? And he said, I
think I'll do a three year retreat, you
know?
So just when he's most famous, just when
he has the most money
just when many students come in
he said, you know, I think I'll do like
a three year retreat. And this is called
Yarlung. This is a special place.
Similar to Diamond Mountain. And then he
went there.
He took I think eight students with him.
If you count the guys in the boat,
there's nine. It's very famous number.
Him and his eight.
And they got in the boat and they he
purposely crossed a big river
to do his retreat so nobody can follow
him.
Uh and he did a long retreat there,
okay? And he said and he left
everything. He left the money. He left
all the stuff.
He just took a few pairs of clothes and
he he went to do his retreat. Cool?
Good idea. All right.
Right here you can see G R V A.
R K Y A N G. Yeah, good. Nice. Who's
doing that? Is that Francisco?
Hafso. Where is Hafso?
There he is. Okay.
Say Java Drolkyem.
Java Drolkyem.
Here's half of the word Drolkyem.
Drolkyem means uh
a good monk who is
solitary, alone.
Alone. So a good monk
uh is happy to stay alone in a house and
do their meditation and things like
that. So it's a very very famous word.
Java Drolkyem means uh
uh single monk. Stay by themself. Just
do their practice. Drolkyem means
Chadel Shikam. Chadel Chadel means he
gave up all of his fame. He gave up all
of his many projects and he went to do
retreat.
Bun Bunlo means the master. Lo means his
disciples.
Gu nine, okay? Eight plus one. Uh
Mushogye, they have
$8.
Okay, they put all their money together.
It's $8, okay?
And they're happy for the whole retreat.
They're okay.
You know, they survive and they're
happy.
They're happy. They feel happy and they
did a nice retreat, okay?
And their clothing was just kind of old
robes and they're happy. They're fine.
They don't need more than that, okay?
Nine $8, nine guys.
How they split it, I don't know.
Okay.
All right. Segye Sokyi.
Uh Nyamlen By the way, Francisco, you
got to have my
uh hang on. In other Cinco Casas de
Cinco Casas de Proyeccion. Listo.
Uh
half hour, okay? All right.
Say good talking young men and young
women during the summer
long check on
Yeah, you don't have to worry about
going to look for
property and nice clothes. Let your
karma do the shopping.
Okay? Let your karma do the shopping. I
like that. Okay, you don't have to
stress
too much, you know? Be generous
with other people. Be kind to other
people.
And let your karma do the shopping.
Things will come to you.
Okay? Things will come to you. And they
do they do come. They come to me. I
I just let my karma do the shopping. I I
rarely go shopping. Okay?
Once every six months I go to
Takashimaya to buy
gift for my wife or something. Okay,
then letting your karma do the shopping
and staying calm
when other people criticize you. They
are connected. Okay? Understand? There's
a connection.
Just happy. Let your karma buy the
clothes.
And just be happy. People complain to
you. You like
it They are like old clothes.
Understand? Irritating people.
Do you like old clothes? Yes.
Can you survive with irritating people?
Yeah, it's okay. I don't care. I don't
listen to them.
You know?
That's the definition of Geshe.
They don't listen to anybody.
Okay?
After 25 years they can
argue that the sky is not blue and and
they can succeed.
Okay.
Next picture.
This is a nice I like this sentence.
Kache means
tapas like difficult spiritual practice.
Okay?
And then
here he makes a suggestion of one
difficult spiritual practice and
so in my three-year retreat I did a lot
of yoga and I wanted to learn ballet.
And every six months one ballet teacher
will come and she will teach me.
She actually later she told me I'm
hopeless.
She said I can teach anyone except you.
You can't remember three steps. When you
after the first step you forgot the
second step.
It's true and but anyway
so
I I studied ballet for three years with
her and I still do some and then she
said
she said I'll give you a suggestion, you
know? And I said what? She said you
practice every day
like one hour. You practice your ballet
every day one hour and
and then she said you know what? There's
a system you can practice ballet
all day.
And I'm like what do you mean, you know?
And she said suppose you are in the
kitchen and you are cooking in the
kitchen
and you you are cooking at the stove and
you have to turn around and go to the
table. Don't just
gosh you might don't walk like that, you
know? Go
and go to the table and pick up
something and come back
and be graceful.
You know? She said you can do ballet all
day. You don't have to wait for one hour
practice. Okay?
And my Dharma teacher also told me
you can do this kache. Kache means
it's kind of a yoga practice you can do
the whole day and it's sit up straight.
Okay? And he taught me and
sometimes with a stick.
And now I got the habit, you know?
And it's it's very healthy for you. You
have a central channel sushumna.
Some people have two sushumnas.
And
and if you keep it straight your your
mind will be better. Your mind will be
stronger. Okay? So keep your back
straight.
Your back's not straight. Your back goes
like this but
it feels straight if you sit up
straight. Okay? And then your mind will
be clear more clear.
So here he says
keep your patience with your Dharma
practice
even just sitting up all day. Even just
don't you know don't sit like
Okay. All right. Like
Okay.
Kache lungi dingy dong lang then be
happy. Kunjoe chepa sochu yoso jimbela
dembe dingy dong lang.
If you have to Recently we have a nice
project to build some stupas
and it's a lot of work and you know we
go out in the desert and we carry rocks
and we build the stupa and
be happy. You know? It's a it's a nice
practice. Okay?
Sokme dupatang
kung yimbe so jinda chunya den a ma tang
chugi dong dugi che bang le
chunya ne dobatsola dembe dingy dong
lang
If you have some kind of
problem
I don't know.
You have physical problem. You can also
be patient about yourself.
You know? Your body is not cooperating.
You try to do yoga you hurt yourself.
Something. Your hair is taking a
vacation.
Then you know? Don't get all
Okay. It's part of life. Okay? It's part
of life. Your body will get old. Your
face will get old.
You know? And a Buddhist
is graceful. Get old gracefully. You
know?
Yes I have lots of wrinkles. Yes. I
Every wrinkle I have was created by 100
students.
So I'm proud of my wrinkles. You know? I
can remember
the students in that place and I can
remember the and then each one I I I
earned these wrinkles
and I'm proud of them. Okay? Probably
those students each took three four
hairs each.
It's okay. I I
You should come to the late part of your
life and say I spent my body well.
Okay? Like when you're born they give
you $100. You spend your body. Every
year you spend Your body gets older
and it won't work so good after 10 years
and it
So spend it wisely, you know? Don't
waste the money, you know? Spend it.
Okay? If you have lots of wrinkles
on your face when you're 60 70 because
you worried about many other people.
I think it's beautiful. I think you look
more beautiful.
I think those that kind of wrinkle is
very
elegant.
I think and you earned it, right?
With all those trouble people.
Okay? All right. Bang le de jam nos
about sola dembe dingy dong lang. Gyalwa
sembe trul a dembe dingy dong lang. He
keeps saying dong lang dong lang dong
lang.
Yeah. Dong lang means
accepted gracefully.
Okay? Accepted gracefully. Okay? When
you someone gives you lots of work. Now
the picture.
Francisco the old Yeah.
This is the
ACI director.
Okay?
You know, he's always falling asleep.
It's difficult to have a conversation
with him.
You have to say a few sentences he falls
asleep.
Then you wait and then he wake up and
then you you you say you so tired, you
know?
But that tiredness is like
elegant, you know? Like you can buy
elegant shirt. You can buy elegant
clothes but elegant
exhaustion.
Now that's something beautiful. Okay?
That's really special. You earned it.
Okay?
Kilmechu na dingy dingy.
Erna sembe jimbela so sembe jimbela
dingy dingy dingy dong lang. Songda
shingla so na belta bang damba. You can
also collect wrinkles trying to collect
money
and then you can get extra wrinkles
trying to protect your money.
And then when you get to the end of your
life and you look at those wrinkles in
the mirror they are just stupid
wrinkles.
They are not elegant wrinkles. I rather
have elegant wrinkles. Elegant wrinkles
a little bit here.
You know? And it's not like
Okay. Then this is protecting money
wrinkle.
This is the making the money wrinkle.
And then here's the
I helped the Dharma, you know? Wrinkle
is like
you know?
And it's kind of beautiful wrinkles.
Okay.
Songda shingla so belta che bang bamalo
so.
Chel kicho le dembe dingy dong lang le
so dingy dong.
Yeshindu kyache.
Okay.
Hang on. I My doctor told me to drink
something.
Almond milk.
Mhm.
If you there's also a kind of patience
about your your Buddhism.
And it's described in the Lamrim.
Uh doing your meditation, doing your
practice.
Um
All these Buddhist practices trying to
study Lamrim.
We're going to talk about five houses
uh in about
What time am I supposed to stop?
Bunch bunchy. 40 minutes.
Okay. I'm supposed to stop at 5:00. Yes.
Yeah.
Okay. Got it. Okay.
We'll talk about five houses later
today. But anyway,
uh it's a lot of work. It's how to help
other people, how to spread the Dharma
to other people. Okay?
He's describing
the different kinds of hard work
that you can do in the steps on the
path, Lamrim, or you can do hard work uh
in the background, you know, studying
the ancient books. You can do hard work
in many ways.
And that kind of hard work work is sweet
hard work. And every year it makes you
more and more happy. Okay? Hard work to
make money I I believe, I think every
year it makes you more unhappy. I think
so.
In my just watching people, I I I feel
like that.
And then the people who do hard work for
their Buddhism
uh
they get more and more relaxed every
year. Okay? And and I think that's
something.
I like it. Okay.
Okay. All right.
Especially
dum dum
This is I think the first Lamrim class.
It's Prescott. Okay? If you look
carefully, you can see
you can see the
If you look carefully, you can see the
bedbugs
on people.
Everybody's like
Okay. We couldn't afford a good place.
And we made we bought we rented a very
cheap place and
we share the bed with the bedbugs.
Anyway, uh 70 something.
So he says there's three kinds of
patience.
One is with people who hurt you.
He says in his lecture, I think it was
21 days.
By the way, I don't know how many people
I think a thousand people came to this
Lamrim teaching
around
20 something when he taught. There's no
microphone.
You know, he's teaching a thousand
people. He has to yell.
And
then people in those days they would the
class would take about 8 hours, 10
hours.
They would sit on their butt for 8
hours, 10 hours.
Luckily, they can run outside and pee
pee on
on the ground right there.
I was I was in many of those classes.
Uh
But anyway, there's a kind of patience
you need to study Lamrim also, you know.
It's hard to It's hard to sit.
Uh
year after year it's hard to sit in the
I I know.
Okay, when I studied Geshe course, we
were in a small room. We don't have
money for classroom. We don't have any
school.
We just sit in the teacher's house.
They're in a very cheap uh shack. The
roof always leaks.
You know, everybody knows where the roof
leaks. They try to get there early so
they don't sit there.
And when we are in the class, we can't
move. There's no room to move. And your
knees on top of the other person's
knees.
And if the roof leaks, you cannot move.
You just duck duck duck.
And uh so I
I was sitting there suffering in the
summer, in the monsoon. It's like 45°
outside.
centigrade. And
it's terribly hot and terribly
uncomfortable. And the teacher's like
on and on and on.
No breaks. No breaks in the Geshe
course. There's no such thing.
You just have to sit there three, four
hours, you know, suffer.
And then I made a
quiet
promise to myself
that when I get to become a teacher,
I'll make those guys suffer.
You know,
and they will have to sit there for 14
years
on their bottom. And
like that. So
I did it, right?
Okay.
Uh and then you got to be tough, okay?
To study in the class, you have to be
tough, okay?
It helps if you sit up straight, by the
way. You can sit longer.
And it's not so painful.
My teacher had a special method. Uh I
built him a house.
And I built him a place to teach
uh with my own hands. This happened My
hands got messed up. And uh
And then he said, "I will buy the
furniture." I'm like, "Okay, you buy the
furniture." He bought the most
uncomfortable chair in the world.
It's all wood.
And an open, you know, like folding
chair. Very cheap.
And very great suffering to sit on that
chair, you know. And then I'm like every
I sat on that chair for 25 years.
I'm like, "How can he buy this chair,
you know?"
And
you got to
don't worry about it, okay? You should
thank him. We should thank him, by the
way.
I like this hotel, by the way. It's kind
of
Those uh
university people put me in a very
stuffy old people's hotel.
And Tim put me in a young person's
hotel. I
I like it.
I like the music in the room.
Okay.
Okay. So
he's finishing the perfection of
patience.
And his final part on patience is it
takes patience to sit in the class,
okay? And I know you you don't think
about it like that. You think patience
is only when someone's yelling at you or
somebody's angry or something like that.
But there's a kind of patience.
It takes a lot of patience to sit year
after year
in the class, you know. And
people ask me, "Do you really need to
sit there for 14 years, Geshe La?"
And the answer is no, you need to sit
there for 4,000 years.
Okay? And
you cannot change the human mind.
is more stubborn than stone.
Uh
and it takes years to change the human
mind, okay? And to be honest, you know,
I can teach it to you in in in 2 weeks
or something.
But to change a human being
uh it takes a lifetime of of sitting in
those chair, okay?
So just relax and
you know, enjoy. Enjoy the ride.
Cuz you know, it's not like you're going
to see emptiness in
after two classes or something. It
doesn't work like that, okay?
All right. Uh we reached
uh Sundu
which means uh joyful efforts.
You ready? Let's repeat.
Tsun Kang.
Gela.
Trowa Oh.
Tsun Kang.
Gela.
Trowa Oh.
The fourth perfection
defined by Shantideva. It says work hard
in your Dharma practice and have fun.
And I love that have fun. It's called
Trowa in in Tibetan language. It's
called Trowa. It means uh
Tsun Kang means uh
work hard in in
in virtue.
And then Trowa means have fun, okay? And
I I
I were I I was in the sitting the class
for 50 years. I sat in the class for 50
years.
And uh
and it's true, okay? If you're not
having fun
with your Dharma practice, then you
something's wrong, okay? Then you
If you're all serious and
and all
you know, like something's wrong, okay?
You should be having fun.
Okay? It should be fun and you should
joke with your friends and
play tricks on them and stuff like that,
okay? The whole time. All right? It It
should be fun. You should have fun. When
you come to Kyoto or something Diamond
Mountain
then have a good time. You don't have to
sit in your room and meditate the whole
time, you know. Have some fun, you know?
When Dharma people get together and have
fun, this is also Dharma, okay?
Uh we had a great dinner last night.
We had fun. And by the way, we talked
about Dharma for 4 5 hours.
It was but we also ate I think the
restaurant owner had to close it.
He had to close the restaurant after we
leave.
There's no food left.
Okay.
All right, so now we reached uh
fourth perfection
which is the last one I'm teaching you.
Uh that's the end of the 14 years, okay?
Uh today is the last day, I think.
of the Lamrim. Everybody said,
Don't worry, we're doing more next year.
Uh
different subject.
Next year we start Diamond Way, okay? If
like relax Diamond Way.
Okay, yeah.
Okay.
So uh
So in Buddhism and I remember
all the words that I learned in
Buddhism, I learned them from my
teacher. I did not have a dictionary.
You know, I learned uh
I'm I'm reading the ancient Sanskrit
Tibetan for
50 years, but I never used a dictionary.
I just asked my teacher.
And I remember when I asked him tsöndrü,
you know,
joyful effort, and he he took me, "This
is my My dictionary is a human being
called Lama."
And he he said, "You want the definition
of tsöndrü?" I said, "Yeah." He said,
"Follow me.
This is the perfect dictionary who who
take you."
And he took me outside. We lived in a
very very poor
town and they are all Mongolia
refugee from World War II.
And uh they came to America. They they
got They lived in the worst
town in the very very poor.
And I went out He took me out and he
showed me the neighbor's house, you
know? And this neighbor, he he spent all
his time fixing cars
and trying to make some money, you know?
This is on the
west side of the Russian gambling.
And he's making noise all all all year,
you know? Illegally fixing cars in his
house.
And uh anyway, but he never rests. He
just fixes cars all day all night.
And he said, "Do you think that guy
works hard?"
And I said, "I never saw anybody who
worked that worked so hard." He said,
"That's not hard work."
You know, he said, "Meditation is hard
work. Uh study is hard work.
Be patient with an
uh irritating person.
Uh this is hard work, okay? That's hard
work. So hard work doesn't mean you are
spend many hours at your job and you
came home at midnight and I was in
Tokyo. I I Should I tell them? I
I went to a nightclub all night all
night. We danced all night.
Should I It's okay, right? It was
Dharma dance.
And uh we danced all night. In the
morning we come out and uh in Tokyo and
I saw all the businessmen going home
at 4:00 in the morning, you know? The
sun's coming up and these guys are like
zombie, you know?
And this is not hard work, okay? That's
not hard work, okay? Hard work is
hard work is to have fun
doing Dharma. That's hard work. In
Buddhism
the definition of hard work
is you you do your Buddhism like hungry,
you know? With appetite.
You know, teacher say, "I'm going to
teach you some special class next year."
You're like,
You know, yummy yummy. You know, and
that's that's hard work, okay? That kind
of yummy yummy
that's that's hard work, okay? That's
the fourth perfection. By the way, the
perfections are split
into two groups, okay? Uh basically the
first three
of the six perfections are to make good
karma.
And the last two are to see emptiness,
okay? Meditation
and wisdom, which we studied already.
Those last two perfections are to see
emptiness. The first three perfections
are to make good karma, okay?
And then what about the one in the
middle? What about number four?
That goes both ways.
That goes both ways, okay? I You should
have fun
uh making good karma
and you should have fun with your
meditation and emptiness, okay? So
there's a reason why they put this one
number four. It's supposed to sup-
supply both sides. Wisdom and method,
okay?
All right. Uh I like this picture here.
The
This is the first year I went to study
with my teacher.
Like 1973,
something.
And uh we're just having fun all the
time, okay?
And uh
and I I feel like that's how you should
be, okay?
Tsöndrü Kong Gyaltsen, he quotes that
Gyalwa Tsongkhapa and Tsöndrü Kunga
Gyaltsen.
Having I call it the perfection of
fun.
Okay, fourth perfection.
Okay, what do they call it Sanskrit?
What's the Sanskrit
word?
Uh virya.
Virya paramita. Say virya.
Paramita.
Perfection of fun.
Okay, have fun doing good stuff, okay?
All right. And and really
if you
study Lamrim, if you study Buddhism
and you're not having fun, something's
wrong. You're not You're not doing it
right, okay? If you're very serious,
then
it feels hard and
you're tired all the time,
then there's something wrong. Then you
you're not doing Buddhism. You must be
doing something else.
Okay, you should be having fun, okay?
That's how you can tell if you're doing
Buddhism right, okay?
All right. Uh
Dini Gyaltsen Tsongkhapa Tsongkhapa top
chok day.
Having fun is the way to picture
Francisco.
Is the way to win the race, okay? That's
a Buddhahood line.
She's crossing the Buddhahood line.
You know, she practice practice practice
and now she's crossing the Buddhahood
line. The way to get to the Buddhahood
line and cross the Buddhahood line
is have fun, okay? Otherwise, really you
will never survive. You will never make
it. In my Geshe class we start with 60
guys.
Uh 25 years later, there's two.
Two left.
Okay,
all those serious guys quit.
And the two guys who survived are having
fun.
Okay? Understand? Those very smart guys,
very serious guys, they all quit. Uh and
then two goofballs, Geshe Michael and
the other guy.
We're like,
Yeah, we survived, you know?
Okay? Fun gets you to the finish line.
Okay, the finish line is Buddhahood,
okay? Having fun is what gets you there.
All right, Don again and Gyalwa
Tsongkhapa Tsöndrü Chökyi Gyaltsen
Dede Gyaltsen Tsongkhapa Tsöndrü Kunga
Gyaltsen.
Kunga Gyaltsen Dede Tsongkhapa Ngawang
Drakpa Dende Ngawang Drakpa You get
everything you dream of if you have fun.
Tsöndrü Kunga Gyaltsen
Dede Tsongkhapa Tsöndrü Kunga Gyaltsen
Tsöndrü Ngawang Drakpa Tsöndrü Chökyi
Gyaltsen. You want to get the
Buddhahood, have fun, okay?
Basically, who is that?
Yeah. Okay, Don again. That's
uh Maitreya.
Pretty good guy.
Who is Maitreya?
Buddha number four in this world. But
the Shakyamuni was number three, okay?
Maitreya is number four.
Fu- They call future Buddha, right?
Much closer than you think.
All right, Tsöndrü Ngawang Drakpa Chökyi
Gyaltsen Dede Sangye Kyab Chökyi
Gyaltsen
La.
Okay, he says
uh the best way to get good karma is to
have fun
doing Dharma.
Then when he reaches the perfection of
meditation, he says, "Meditation is the
best way to make good karma and reach
Buddha hood." Then when he every
He said it every time. It's the same
advertisement
for every perfection. But okay,
that's all right.
Uh everything comes from
having fun. Okay.
Number next teacher, Francisco Budo.
Yeah.
Then
I can say
Buddha shape can do Dharma shape.
So I don't know if you ever worked with
donkeys. I mean real donkeys, not the
not your
not your colleagues at your office.
But the real animal.
Uh
So I did when I was a kid, I was a boy
scout.
I'm a eagle boy scout.
I finished it.
And beyond, there's a secret level also
you don't know about.
Uh
anyway,
uh
there's a
We used to go once a month, we used to
go for 3 days uh camping. We go to the
mountains. We hike for 10 miles, 15
miles.
And we go in the mountains and we have
to carry your own water in Arizona.
You have to carry water for 4 days or
something. It's difficult when you're
like 12 years old and you they tell you
if you drink your water, you don't have
any more.
You know, so we we have to carry it. And
then if we go on a long trip,
you have to take a donkey with you cuz
cuz you cannot carry that much water.
And there's no water in Arizona, right?
So anyway,
uh
those are the most stubborn animals you
ever met, okay? They are completely
stubborn.
Stubborn, you know? And they will not
They are worse than any student I ever
had.
Okay? And I had very stubborn students.
I don't know why I have this karma.
But you you put the water on them.
You say, "Okay, let's go. We're going
for a 10-mile hike." And they won't
move. They just won't move, you know?
You hit them with a stick and they're
like
You know, you want to hit me some more,
you know?
Then you get behind them and you push
and then they kick you.
And uh bam, like it can break your leg.
And uh
He's talking about a real donkey, okay?
Uh
so Buddha
yes, in your
Dharma practice, you shouldn't act like
a donkey who's being asked to walk up a
hill.
Okay? You should enjoy yourself, okay?
Don't be grumpy.
And don't be stubborn like a donkey,
okay? Your teacher asks you to do
something. Hey, hey, okay. I'd love to
do that.
And and do it, okay? Like that.
I I wasn't always cheerful.
But I always did what my teacher said,
you know? And that And sometimes I was
grumpy.
So he'd say, "You know, clean this
room." And I'm like
Yes, I'd love to. Thank you.
You know? And
But I I think I can say I always did
what he asked me.
I didn't do it happily. Uh all the And
I'm I made sure he understood I wasn't
happy.
Uh
But I always did it. He had a hundreds
of students. Uh only one survived in his
house.
He kicked them all out.
Only one survived for 25 years, okay?
I just like a donkey, you know?
Okay.
All right.
You know?
Uh the company in the New England
company in the chamber chair cha.
Uh if you're not able to have a lot of
fun at the beginning,
okay, be 90% grumpy and 10% fun.
Okay? Like try to have a little fun so
you get used to it.
And then the rest of it you can be
grumpy, okay? So every day try to have a
little fun
in your Dharma practice and
mostly grumpy is okay. Then you can
increase the fun slowly, okay?
Now he gets to the subject called
laylo. Say laylo.
There's an English idiom called laylo.
Which means to avoid your boss, for
example.
Okay?
And I think it's an interesting
coincidence
that laylo in Tibetan language means
super lazy, okay? And it means the
opposite of having fun.
Okay? So we're going to study You can
call it laziness, but really it's not
having fun.
Okay? It's like
grumpy effort.
This is some animal.
Skunk. Yeah, when I did my 3-year
retreat,
we have skunk. Skunk is a
small animal makes a bad smell.
If they get upset, they make a small
bad very bad smell. It will stay on your
clothes for 1 week or something. They
spray you with some
thing out of their
bottom.
And
so we have one night in my 3-year
retreat, they get inside.
Two of them get inside and they have a
fight. And then
Then
And when they talk, they go like this.
And after I finished 3-year retreat, uh
I met many people like that. Sound
Sound the same.
You know?
Okay. So anyway, here's the three kinds
of
not having fun, okay?
Uh
I'll do the first. You look by laylo me
say gilo.
Gewa Kong Young Chishu. Chishu is a
unusual word in Tibetan. It means you
delay.
You delay. You put out off for tomorrow,
okay?
Will you meditate? Yes. Will you
meditate every day? Yes.
You know? By the way, I keep this stupid
because my students couldn't make a
better one yet.
After many years of asking them.
I use Insight Meditation timer. It's
okay. It's kind of a lot of stupid
things on it.
It irritates me every day. Now it's like
good afternoon. Yeah, good afternoon.
Uh but I used the the timer here, you
know?
And uh
It's funny because uh every day you say,
"Will you I I I have a theory of
meditation." After many years
of teaching meditation,
I I believe to see emptiness directly,
you must meditate for 1 hour. I believe
that. In my experience, you have to.
Uh
I also believe you cannot start
with more than 10 minutes of meditation.
It's foolish. It's not possible. If you
didn't meditate before,
if you don't meditate every day,
if you used to meditate and you don't
meditate,
and you're waiting to start again,
which happens to me many times, okay? In
the
Dharma,
in Buddhism, you don't go like this,
okay? Nobody in history, even Buddha
didn't go like this.
Uh you always go like this.
But you got to keep going up, okay? Like
this. You never go like like the smooth
line, you know?
Then every day is like beautiful day. It
doesn't work like that. If you If you
want that, forget it. You go someplace
else.
Okay? It always you go go good good good
good good good crash.
Airplane crash.
Life crash.
Relationship crash. Financial crash.
Then Then you got to get back up, okay?
Be miserable for 1 week. It's okay.
Like don't meditate. Don't practice. Be
mean to everybody.
Don't be Buddhist for 1 week.
Then you got to get back on the horse,
you know? Then you climb back on the
horse. Start again, okay? Start again.
By the way, I'm looking at Candy like
Can you stand up?
Uh please. Yeah.
Uh
I asked her many years ago to do a
project to help some child I built a
school for homeless children
many years ago. And uh I I paid for the
school. It was expensive.
And uh then I asked her to take care of
the kids. And I met her
few days ago and she said, "Geshe La,
you know I'm still doing taking care of
the kids
for like I don't know, 15 years or
something. So I want to thank her.
Yeah.
All all homeless kids, okay? All
homeless kids. And she she took care of
them many years.
I forgot she's taking care of them.
Then she gave me a report. I'm like,
"Wow,
that's cool. Okay, anyway, your practice
will be like that. Your meditation will
be like that. Don't expect some
you know, smooth road to Buddhahood. It
doesn't exist, okay? If someone try to
sell you that,
forget it, you know?
All right, it doesn't exist, okay? Just
you're going to have problems. You're
going to have disaster. You're going to
have breakdown. Every time you
stop meditating,
okay? And I And stop I mean real stop. I
mean 1 month, 2 months,
you know, you're too busy to meditate.
Every day you're like, "I'll meditate
tomorrow. I'll meditate tomorrow."
That's called here chisha. Here chisha
in the book chisha.
Chisha means,
"Oh, you know, I I I messed up my
meditation practice.
I couldn't meditate for a week.
Definitely next week I'll start again."
And then you don't, okay? And you you
know, it goes like that. I did it a
hundred times, okay? I did it a hundred
times. My suggestion today
about this topic, chisha. Say chisha.
Start back with 10 minutes, okay? Get
the stupid inside app until my students
finish my better one.
They're also chisha-ing.
Uh
use this thing. It has a timer.
I'll I'll play for you. I like it. They
have a good bell. They don't have any
good information, but it's a good bell.
Uh
no, just kidding.
It's a cool bell. I like to
They have many bells. I I like this one
cuz when I finish my meditation, I like
to come out kind of peacefully. I don't
like a bong.
You know? So, uh
So, anyway, just 10 minutes, okay? Start
back with 10 minutes.
And then my advice, really, and this is
the most precious thing I can teach you
this week, okay?
Start back with 10 minutes. I don't care
if you used to meditate for 1 hour,
2 hours, I don't care.
When you have a breakdown, when you have
a meditation breakdown, I
What's the definition of breakdown,
Geshe la? More than 1 week you quit.
Okay? If you quit 2 3 days, you can just
keep going. That's okay. If you quit for
more than 5 6 days,
then start again at 10 minutes, okay?
Start over at 10 minutes.
And
a day, 10 minutes a day.
But real 10 minutes a day. And then uh
this thing has a timer.
Uh
I I will increase it uh
I will increase it 1 minute
every Sunday.
Once a week I will increase 1 minute,
okay? So, next week I'm doing
11. The next week I'm doing 12 minutes,
okay? I'm proud to say
This says 8,982
minutes Geshe la finished uh on this
stupid app. I mean uh
I but I appreciate the app, actually. Uh
So, I I did it for myself.
Okay? Now it's set on uh 34 minutes.
It means I started over 24 weeks ago. I
had a meditation breakdown
25 weeks ago. And I didn't meditate for
more than a week.
And then I started over. I can tell. So,
now I have 34 minutes. So, I did 24
weeks.
I increased 1 minute every week for 24
weeks. Now I'm up to 34. I can tell.
It's been half a year I didn't break my
meditation. But I predict I will have a
breakdown.
All right, okay.
And
I'm practicing for perfection. When I
have a breakdown, I smile.
I'm like, "You stupid guy." You know?
Like, "Yeah."
"Why couldn't you meditate?" "I don't
know.
I was busy, you know?" And then you know
you have to start over at 10 minutes.
I'm like, "Really?"
"I'm a Geshe." Yeah, Geshe.
Geshe also have to start over 10
minutes.
You know? Okay. All right.
Okay, and
and keep your
keep your meditation, okay? So, chisha
means you delay. You delay and you
delay, okay?
Uh I want to talk to you a little bit of
By the way, we finished the 14 years,
okay? You ready? Yeah.
Oh,
uh I have a little bit more in the
second class, yeah.
A little bit more, but I wanted to talk
about something else for a little bit.
Uh
what do we do next year?
And uh what do we do for the next
hundred years?
I I would like So, me and Tim we talked
for a long long long time.
And I told you the general plan for the
classes. So, basically ACI has four
events big events every year. We do two
retreats at Diamond Mountain Retreat
Center in Arizona.
We do one weekend retreat in Mexico City
in the summer.
And we do one winter retreat in Kyoto.
In Around No, am I am I am I right?
Yeah. And I I like it. I think it gives
you some time.
It's good to come to class. It's good to
learn real Buddhism.
And it's good to take it home and
practice it before you eat more.
Okay? You can get indigestion
if you just take classes all the time.
You should take classes, learn
something, and then go home and do it
for a while.
And then come back and and take more
classes and then go home. And So, it's a
good schedule. I like the schedule. You
don't have to come to Arizona. You you
know,
you don't have to go to Mexico. You
don't have to come to Kyoto. You're
welcome to take it online.
You know, I
in the beginning I was stubborn. I said,
"No, there's a blessing
to be in the same room with your
teacher. There is a blessing."
But it's uh there's also a blessing to
go to hell after you die.
And
it's better to take some Dharma. If you
don't have time, you have to work, you
have family, it's expensive to go to
Kyoto all the time. And if you
I'm happy to teach you online. That's
fine, okay? So, don't go crazy. Let's
meet together when it's comfortable for
you. When you have enough money, when
you have enough time,
uh let's meet together in person. If you
don't have time, online is fine, okay?
It's It's fine.
And we can do that four times a year.
And uh we we will go through
two texts, okay?
One is called
uh Devil Meets the Angel or Debates
Between the Devil and the Angel. It's
called Dungs and Shungdrup in Tibetan.
Uh
It means uh you know that picture in
your mind there's a devil and a angel
and they're fighting. The angel the
devil say,
"Just before class,
your friends walking towards Takashimaya
and they want to go into the chocolate
croissant shop."
And then the angel, which is my wife
over here,
she's like,
"You promised me you wouldn't eat those
chocolate croissants in Kyoto."
Then there's a debate in your own mind,
right? So, there's a beautiful beautiful
ancient book. It's
400 years old. It's all poetry.
It's called the
Angel and the Devil in one person's mind
have a fight.
And they fight about emptiness. The
whole book is about emptiness. And it's
a long
and it's deep. And uh I've been teaching
it for years, 8 9 years.
And I never have time to finish it. And
I I I always lose the
I lose the flow
because there's so many weeks between
months, years.
So, I just want to finish it, you know?
My teacher also did not finish it. He
taught it to us and he couldn't finish
it. So, I'm like, "I want to finish it."
So, next year next year
we'll finish it, okay? That's emptiness.
That's for your meditation.
And that's for your emptiness, okay? At
the same time,
uh in the first year we will finish a
famous famous short lamrim. Just take 1
year.
Not 14 years, okay? Traditionally,
if you want to study Diamond Way,
you should do a fresh lamrim.
So, we'll do a fresh lamrim for 1 year.
I'll trans Me and Gibson translate the
book. We'll publish the book. Rosa will
publish the book. Grandpa will finish
it.
And uh
That's what we'll do next year. So,
every every time you come to
ACI with Grandpa,
we will do this uh
we'll do the
emptiness book
and then we'll we'll do the Lam Rim.
Then after that we'll start a very very
beautiful
book about Diamond Way and that was
written by the same person who wrote
this book.
Okay, it's Pabongka Rinpoche, okay? And
he wrote he was a great
Diamond Way practitioner, Vajrayogini.
Female Buddha, highest Buddha, female.
She's female.
And he he was a great great master.
And my teacher taught me that book for
for 30 years.
Okay, my teacher taught me that book. We
went to it several times.
Then I translated it and it's secret.
You you cannot buy the book, right?
And
I'll teach it to you, okay?
First you have to finish the Lam Rim.
The baby Lam Rim.
Next year and then we'll go slow.
And
there's an 18
course 30,000 page Diamond Way course if
you're super serious.
If you'd like to be a teacher at Diamond
Way, you should finish that course with
John Brady or Connie or Earl or these
other people who are teaching.
Geshe Kelsang Gyaltsen, other people,
Ellie.
You know, if you're super serious you
should finish that course, okay? It's
the greatest Diamond Way course ever
done in history.
It's complete. No one has ever done it.
I studied at the time at the Tantric
College. There's only two Tantric
Colleges.
And I was there.
I debated there and uh
there's nothing like that. There's
nothing like that course. So if you're
serious take that course from one of my
students.
And there's many who there's
how many 80 people finished it?
Something like that, okay?
But I'll teach you a
gentle and enjoyable and fun
Diamond Way, okay? And at the same time
you can do both or you can do either
one. Who's texting me? Oops, okay.
Vajrayogini.
Whoa, okay.
No screaming.
Okay, so you can uh
that's the plan for next year and we're
going to do a thing called Five Houses,
okay?
Five Houses means up to now
ACI we did 14 years of steps on the
path.
And we would like to
um
make a new structure change in in ACI.
We call it the Five Houses, okay? Why?
Uh right now and by the way it's going
to take me
I know I'm over time, I'm sorry.
But I don't care.
Give me 10 minutes, okay?
Give me 10 minutes, I'm sorry.
Uh
So up to now you can you can take the
basic ACI courses, 18 courses. I
designed it for 7 years.
Then you can take the Diamond Way
courses which is
7 more years, that's 14 years.
And if you take all the YSI courses
that's another
6 years, so that's 20 years.
And then I don't know. You know, you can
go like that. There's there's Grandpa
wrote 30 40 years of courses.
And
I don't want to
I I I would like to create a system with
ACI called Five Houses
and you can specialize.
We want to make more teachers. I don't
want to ask someone to
study for 40 years to become a teacher.
I think in a you can become a good
teacher in 5 years or two 4 years or
something, okay?
So I want to give you a chance to
specialize
in a certain subject that you like to
learn. Like I would like to be a
meditation teacher.
Or I would like to be
uh
ancient book teacher or I would like to
be a
Diamond Way teacher. You see? So we
create Five Houses. It's called Five
Houses.
And I'll tell you the Five Houses and
I'll tell them quick, I'm sorry not
everybody has to peepee.
Let's go Francisco.
What's the first one?
Tim got to help me.
Classics House, okay? So you're you have
five options, okay?
For the next few years, okay? You If you
want to be a teacher if you want to be a
teacher, okay?
Who wants to be teacher? Everybody. Who
shouldn't be a teacher? Nobody.
I told you that the first day.
Okay, you don't have choice actually.
I'm giving you five choices about what
you don't have a choice.
Okay, number one
uh
You you teach the classics, okay? That's
the 18
um that's the 18 ACI courses, okay?
Those are the classics, okay? That's the
Geshe course.
I took the 25 year course and I I put it
into a 7 year course. You can finish it
in maybe 5 years.
Okay, so if you are attracted
to the ancient books, if if you And some
people are and some people are not,
let's be honest, okay? Some people
they when they eat an ancient book it's
like a better than a chocolate
croissant. I don't know how.
But
some people like it, okay? So you can
choose. You can make this choice. If you
want to you can be a classics teacher.
Do I have to learn Sanskrit? Do I have
to learn Tibetan? Do I have to learn
Chinese? No, not necessarily. You can
teach the classics. We did all the work
for you. You can become a classics
teacher. You don't have to learn a
foreign language, okay?
It's good to know some words like lelo.
Lazy.
Okay, all right. That's the first house.
It's called the House of Classics, okay?
And you can
uh we will have a course maybe 4 5 years
you can become a teacher in the House of
Classics. How did we get these houses?
I went to back to Princeton recently
with the university group. I saw all the
houses that I used to be a member of
this house and I used to be a member of
this house. There are houses
like Woodrow Wilson School. I'm I'm
I'm a graduate I'm a
scholar at the Woodrow Wilson School.
This is the one of the
elite
political schools in the world. And I
belong to that house and uh you can you
can join different houses at Princeton.
Then I thought that would be cool for
ACI.
You know, so anyway you can join
Classics House if you enjoy it. Some
people like
Okay, another choice.
Uh Samadhi House
and this means I would like to be a
meditation teacher.
Okay, I would like to be a meditation
teacher and with then you can finish a 4
year program 5 year program. By the way
you can join a house before you finish
the house.
You know, you can join
you know, meditation house, Samadhi
house or you can join Classics House
from the first day.
Okay, in in Princeton you pledge. It's
called pledge. Pledge means you go to
the
you go to the I don't know, Classics
House and you say, "I want to be a
teacher of the classics." And in the
first day they let you join, okay?
If you don't finish
the course after a few years they kick
you out.
But you can join from the first day,
okay? So
you know, basically you can join any of
the Five Houses.
Very easy, you just finish your five 18
courses, okay?
No, you have to finish five courses. If
you join a house you have to commit to
finish five of the traditional ACI
courses. It's not much. It take maybe
8 months 9 months something like that.
We want everyone
who joins a house should have the same
foundation
of minimum five ACI courses, okay?
And they're the sweet ones. They're the
easy ones.
Okay, second house Samadhi House, okay?
I want to be a meditation teacher. I
want to join. Then you can pledge.
Pledge means you can go to Tim and say,
"I I really attracted to Samadhi House.
I'm not so attracted to Classics House.
Can I be in Samadhi House?" And Tim will
say
"Finish your five courses, come back,
talk to me, okay? Or no, we'll sign you
up and then you're going to promise to
finish the five courses, okay? That's
all. All right, easy. Easy peasy."
All right, number three.
The hotel I'm sorry,
let's be patient with Grandpa.
Okay,
third one.
Huh?
Mountain House. Say Mountain House.
Yeah, this means I would like to learn
to be a retreat master. I would like to
be a retreat master. I'd be like to be
like Cat or Gelsey sitting on the
mountain.
And people climb the mountain and say,
"I want to learn to do a deep retreat
for 3 years. Cat, we have many 3-year
retreats here."
And she said, "Oh, okay. You can do it.
Go in this cave. Fight with the snakes."
You know, just kidding.
But
No, not kidding. Uh
Not really. Okay. But some people just
in their heart they're attracted. They
read the story about those great
meditators on the mountain. In Japan you
have Saicho.
And you have great meditators here on
the mountains. Famous 1,000 years ago.
And uh
it's attractive to you. You feel
You like it. You want to try.
So you can be a retreat master. We call
mountain master. Okay.
Mountain master. Okay, that's a
third option. It requires training.
But like 4 or 5 years training you
become a
retreat master. And you can
you can help other people do retreat.
Retreat doesn't have to be
uh
you know
sit in a cave for 2 years or something
like that. We have a innovation retreat
program.
Uh we have a beautiful program of
retreat for business people.
And And I I used
I used business retreats for for 19
years in Manhattan.
Uh I I I went on a retreat every few
months.
And I invented many
important
business inventions. Uh which is why our
company became quarter billion dollar
and we sold it to Warren Buffett.
And And that's because I did retreats.
It's a secret. Okay. The people in my
company know.
Cuz they suffer when I'm not there.
But I disappear for 1 week, 2 weeks.
And so we have a program like that. If
you're
we can do that. Okay, next one.
Stairway Stairway?
Staircase master.
Staircase master means Lamrim. Okay.
I I'm I'm interested in Lamrim. I like
it.
I like this book that you taught for 14
years. I like it better than the 18
courses.
I like the Lamrim better. No, some
people like this one better.
And some people like the other one
better. And Buddha said
do what you enjoy.
You know, have fun. If I'm not a
I'm not a classics Guess what? I hate
Tibetan grammar.
I never want to see it again.
Okay, then be a retreat teacher, you
know. Be a meditation teacher. You have
a choice, okay? So you can be a Lamrim
teacher. It's very sweet.
Uh
it's more accessible for many people,
okay?
Uh
and you're welcome to learn that, okay?
Next one.
Uh Diamond Way master, okay?
Uh secret teachings master, okay?
And uh some people say, "I want to be a
Diamond Way master." So then you have to
join
Diamond House, okay? And you have that
option also.
Diamond Way teaching doesn't have to be
very strange or very weird or or like
that, okay?
I'll tell you a story, then we'll
finish, okay?
Uh
If you study Diamond Way
properly twice a month
you have to go out for a special meal
with your other Diamond Way
people.
And we went to a place in New York
called Caravan of Dreams.
It's on
6th Avenue and
6th Street and 6th for
6th Street and 4th Avenue.
And uh it's underground actually. It's
dirty. It's It's not very nice. It's a
small restaurant. And we went there and
we did our
you know, Diamond Way
dinner which we're supposed to do twice
a month, you know. Okay.
And there's a big Jewish lady
uh waitress.
And in in New York uh the waitress she
doesn't serve you the
dish. She throws it at you.
And you have
You have to catch it. She's like,
"Blah."
And she's like, "Come on, you guys. Sit
down."
And you know, we're like She's just
you know, and she's like loud
noisy lady, you know. And she Then
finally we had a nice dinner. We
finished.
And
uh we asked
We We We asked her She came back to the
table. We asked her uh
Can we have the bill? We need to go.
You know. And she She goes like this.
"You think I'm going to give you a
bill?"
And we're like, "Yeah, we want a bill."
She says, "You are here. You are Diamond
Way people.
You're doing your your two dinners every
every month. You think I'm going to take
money from you? Get out of here."
We're like
Then she just go to the kitchen, you
know. Then we're like
"Oh, where'd you go, Ginny?"
"Where'd you go, Ginny?"
"Yeah."
"Wow." We run to the kitchen. This is
old cook, you know, retired guy.
We say We say, "Where's the
waitress? Where's the big lady?"
"Huh?"
"You know, the big lady, the waitress,
the one who throw the dish at you."
"There's no lady here."
"There's no
There's no lady like that here."
"We never had a lady like that." You
know, we're like
Wow. That's Diamond Way.
Okay, understand?
That's Diamond Way. Okay. It's not like
long ding ding ding ding ding. And
Okay, have a fun dinner.
Don't pay.
Pissy magic lady show up.
Talk like New York.
Uh
that's Diamond Way, okay? It's super
fun, okay? Anyway, now nobody going to
join the other house then.
Uh
All right. That's all. So we will have
this structure called five houses.
Uh
I was thinking next class. What do you
think? Yeah. And uh
Let Tim know. Let ACI know. There's
something on the website.
You can sign up. You can say, "I'd like
to try this house."
And give it some thought. Don't don't
decide Don't vote for free dinner right
away.
Uh
okay. Just think about it. What you'd
like to do, okay?
But I I believe all of you have a seed.
If you are here
you have a seed to be a teacher. You
have a seed to be a teacher. And it's
fun.
And it's a excellent karma.
If you want to get rich or you want to
be happy or you want to have a good
relationship be a teacher.
Be a good teacher. And And all of this
karma is um it's the best karma you can
make. Everything will come.
You will get everything you dreamed of,
okay?
So think about the five houses. Everyone
in this room
can be a five-house teacher. You You
don't have to
Don't think you can be a teacher. That's
a super stupid, okay?
Everybody in this room
if you made it to this room and 7
billion 900 million 900 didn't make it
here
you are here. So then you are special.
Everyone in this room can be a teacher.
Especially you have five choices, you
know, okay?
So think about it. And
And then we'll start next year, okay?
All right. So we'll start three things.
We'll start the
debate in the mind. We'll start the
Diamond Way preparation.
And we'll start the five houses with
Tim. Anything else, Uncle Tim?
With the this thing I'm doing later,
okay?
Good. Bueno.
That's coming. That's coming.
All right. All right.
Official pee-pee break. What time we
come back, Tim?
How about 5:45?
5:45?
Okay. 5:45.
Okay. See you then. Thank you. Okay.